<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>future of work | IOPsychist</title>
    <link>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/tag/future-of-work/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://iopsychist.netlify.app/tag/future-of-work/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>future of work</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2024</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>future of work</title>
      <link>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/tag/future-of-work/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>I presented at The 11th Annual Conference on Human Capital Innovation in Technology &amp; Analytics (slides attached)</title>
      <link>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/post/recap-the-11th-annual-conference-on-human-capital-innovation-in-technology-analytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/post/recap-the-11th-annual-conference-on-human-capital-innovation-in-technology-analytics/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/post/recap-the-11th-annual-conference-on-human-capital-innovation-in-technology-analytics/index.en_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;the-11th-annual-conference-on-human-capital-innovation-in-technology-analytics&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The 11th Annual Conference on Human Capital Innovation in Technology &amp;amp; Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April, I had my first opportunity to present at an academic conference - the 11th Annual Conference on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nyu.engineering/events/2022/04/26/11th-annual-conference-human-capital-innovation-technology-analytics&#34;&gt;Human Capital Innovation in Technology and Analytics&lt;/a&gt; at NYU. This year’s topic was “The Great Resignation: How Analytics Can Help”. I spoke about some of the work I’ve been involved in with Frank Mo and the Human Capital Analytics Lab to forecast job demand in the Knowledge Worker and Service Worker industries. I learned quite a bit through the process of preparing for, presenting, and discussing our work. It was very cool to hear what the other presenters were working on in their companies and research institutes as well. Also among the speakers were team members from the Conference Board, Accenture, Microsoft, and Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson - quite a lineup to follow!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our research, we worked with data from &lt;a href=&#34;http://candogram.com&#34;&gt;Candogram&lt;/a&gt; - an awesome company that provides job market education to students and, in doing so, processes 2 million job ads per day from 10,000 US employers - and from the BLS &lt;a href=&#34;http://https://www.bls.gov/jlt/&#34;&gt;Job Openings and Labor Turnover survey (JOLTS)&lt;/a&gt;. Our central research question looked at the spike in voluntary quits during the Great Resignation as a precipitating event for changes in labor market demand. To uncover insight into this, we tested two advanced time series forecasting methods - Facebook’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://facebook.github.io/prophet/&#34;&gt;Prophet&lt;/a&gt; model and LinkedIn’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.linkedin.com/blog/2021/greykite--a-flexible--intuitive--and-fast-forecasting-library&#34;&gt;Silverkite&lt;/a&gt; model. It turns out there is a relationship between job quits and job demand, but it depends on which industry you’re looking at!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently working on a white paper which we hope to release in the next few weeks but you can get a sneak peak into what we found from the slide deck from our presentation. This is just the start and there are many future directions we are considering. In the meantime, we’d love to hear your thoughts and feedback! Stay tuned for further updates coming soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_1.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_2.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_3.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_4.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_5.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_6.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_7.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_8.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_9.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_10.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_11.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_12.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_13.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_14.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_15.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_16.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_17.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_18.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_19.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_20.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://iopsychist.netlify.app/hcita_2022_21.jpeg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;font color=&#34;grey&#34;&gt; Originally posted: July 11, 2022&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of Sign-on and Retention Bonuses on Extrinsic Motivation</title>
      <link>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/post/the-impact-of-sign-on-and-retention-bonuses-on-extrinsic-motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/post/the-impact-of-sign-on-and-retention-bonuses-on-extrinsic-motivation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;br&gt;  
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;5&#34;&gt;A recent&lt;/font&gt; SHRM survey found that during the tight labor market spurred by the Covid-19 pandemic, companies &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shrm.org/resourcesandtools/hr-topics/compensation/pages/employers-rely-on-incidental-bonuses-amid-tight-labor-market.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“stepped up their use of sign-on, referral, spot and retention bonuses to attract and keep employees.”&lt;/a&gt; One company found that job ads &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/jackkelly/2021/09/08/companies-are-paying-100000-sign-on-bonuses-to-attract-workers/?sh=2488ad2d3b9f&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;offering a sign-on bonus have increased across all sectors by a whopping 454%, from 10,312 positions in August 2020 to 57,123 in August 2021.”&lt;/a&gt; These types of rewards, also called &lt;strong&gt;incidental rewards&lt;/strong&gt;, have been used to effectively increase employee earnings during the pandemic.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
div.blue { background-color:#e6f0ff; border-radius: 5px; padding: 20px;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div class = &#34;blue&#34;&gt;
SHRM survey fast facts:  
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;52 percent of respondents increased the number of sign-on bonuses awarded in the past 12 months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;49 percent have increased the number of retention bonuses awarded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;5&#34;&gt;Prior&lt;/font&gt; to the pandemic, real wage growth in the US was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2018/08/07/for-most-us-workers-real-wages-have-barely-budged-for-decades/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;relatively stagnant&lt;/a&gt; despite hot job markets and a substantial increase in productivity. This discrepancy disproportionately affected lower income brackets, contributing to further inequality in earnings. These low-skilled jobs often form a company&amp;rsquo;s front-line workforce - a.k.a. those with the highest risk of infection during a pandemic. Covid-19 forced a lot of companies to recognize the importance of these employees to their operating models. It is quicker and easier to provide one-time bonuses or extra-salary compensation than adjust the entire compensation framework for a company. As a policy, it is also easier to unwind post pandemic. Together with increased competition for labor, this was a quick way for companies to respond as the tight market dynamics arose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;5&#34;&gt;However,&lt;/font&gt; rewards based on participation or engagement (as opposed to performance-based rewards) are perhaps the most detrimental type of reward to internal motivation. Why is this important? While the difference between a wage increase and a bonus may be important to employers, the total earnings are more salient to employees than the method by which they were received. Given that we&amp;rsquo;ve now been operating in &amp;lsquo;pandemic-mode&amp;rsquo; for over 20 months, employees may come to expect the total package they are receiving. Furthermore, these bonuses provide extrinsic motivation which works to shift workers&#39; motivation away from any intrinsic sources they have conceived of previously. &lt;strong&gt;All else being equal, it is harder to shift from extrinsic to intrinsic motivation&lt;/strong&gt;. When these external rewards dry up, companies will face challenges in motivating their employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;font size=&#34;5&#34;&gt;From&lt;/font&gt; an I/O perspective, employee motivation should be an important consideration when deciding how to maneuver. This awareness may not make it into the room where compensation and bonus decisions are being made. Viewed purely from a financial lens it may seem attractive to roll back variable pay. However, rolling back expected earnings may hurt employee motivation, thereby decreasing productivity. This loss in output per employee may incur more overall costs to the company in the form of presenteeism, loss of organizational citizenship behavior, and increased hiring costs. &lt;mark&gt;Whether these externalities cost the company more than the compensation savings is a question each employer will have to answer for themselves.&lt;/mark&gt; Regardless, unwinding pandemic-era cash incentives will be a line that employers must navigate as they carve a path forward, and is not as simple as simply returning to the way things were pre-Covid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;font color=&#34;grey&#34;&gt; Originally posted: February 2, 2022&lt;/font&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
