<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>TA | IOPsychist</title>
    <link>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/tag/ta/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://iopsychist.netlify.app/tag/ta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>TA</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2024</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/media/sharing.png</url>
      <title>TA</title>
      <link>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/tag/ta/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opening a New Position</title>
      <link>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/post/opening-a-new-position/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/post/opening-a-new-position/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When a new position is opened, the hiring manager should be able to express the why, the what, the when, and the where behind the position. This includes the reason the position is being requested, what the position will be responsible for and what projects the incumbent will likely be part of, when the position will be needed and the hours per week the position will require, and where the position will need to be located, among other relevant details to the position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to explain these aspects up front is important for a few reasons. It ensures the position (and, therefore, the need for the position) has been carefully considered and determined to be appropriate. The recruitment process requires significant time, energy, and money from the hiring team, the recruiting team, and candidates. If there is not a clear reason for the position, it should be reconsidered whether the role is necessary at the current time. Furthermore, hiring and onboarding a new employee requires time, resources, and has potential long-term impact for the company – good or bad. While it may be tempting to bring on additional help as needed, answering these questions up front will ensure that the benefits and costs are appropriately weighed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tactically, being able to communicate these questions at the beginning of the process to the recruiting team will greatly improve the efficiency and effectiveness of the recruiting process. With a clear understanding of the need to have and nice to have aspects of the position, as well as the fit within the organization, the recruiting team is able to more accurately source and evaluate candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think of the hiring process like searching for a car to buy.&lt;/strong&gt; You (the hiring manager) may know you want a good commuter car that can hold your family comfortably. This would be equivalent to knowing the job title of the opening. If you were to ask someone to find you the right car for your needs, there would be quite a range of options for them to select – likely some which you’re not interested in. Furthermore, once you’ve narrowed your search down to a specific make/model (say, after you’ve reviewed a few ‘candidate cars’ or done further research), there are still more details that are important. Do you want new or used? What color interior or exterior? Do you want to spring for some of the enhanced features? All of them? None of them? So, while you started with what may be thought of as a well-defined need (i.e. commuter car that can hold your family), we see that there are actually numerous other details to consider. Imagine if you provided preferences on the color, new vs used, perhaps even the make and model up front. There would still be details to choose between of course (based on what’s available on the market in your area at the time of your search) but you would have sped up the selection process considerably, possibly giving you access to cars available on the market that you might have been too late for with the previous approach. Now, imagine that you are searching for 50 cars a year, and you are losing money each day that the search lasts. This is why detailed requests &lt;em&gt;up front&lt;/em&gt; are important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To facilitate this, when a new position is opened, the recruiter (or coordinator) responsible for working on the position should have an intake discussion with the hiring manager. Using the example intake form below, they will be able to review the position details and align on the needs of the hiring manager. While not all the possible questions may be answerable up front, and while things may change over the course of the recruiting process, the team should aim as much as possible for accuracy and completeness of these answers. Also, keep in mind that the recruiter will need to be able to describe the opening to candidates and build up excitement for the opportunity. Completing the intake will save the company money, enhance the quality of candidates and hires, and increase the velocity of hiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;example-new-job-intake-form&#34;&gt;Example New Job Intake Form&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Role and Responsibilities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
What will this person be doing?&lt;br&gt;
Need to haves?&lt;br&gt;
Nice to haves?&lt;br&gt;
Specific projects they can expect to work on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Candidate Details&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Target candidate profile?&lt;br&gt;
Anti-patterns to watch out for?&lt;br&gt;
Possible career paths?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Position details&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Backfill or new position?&lt;br&gt;
Location:&lt;br&gt;
Hours:&lt;br&gt;
Pay:&lt;br&gt;
When is this position targeted to come onboard:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team details&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Who do they report to?&lt;br&gt;
How big is the current team? &lt;br&gt;
Management/supervisory duties?&lt;br&gt;
Who else will this person interact with regularly?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Looking back on a successful hire, what will this new hire have done to be considered as such in the first&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
30 days?&lt;br&gt;
90 days?&lt;br&gt;
Year?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interview process&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
What will the typical interview process look like for this position?&lt;br&gt;
Who is part of the interview team?&lt;br&gt;
What will each of them be looking at?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to sell the role&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Why would someone choose this position over another option?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything else that will be important for (Recruiter or RC) to know as they review and screen candidates?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
Incorporating the intake form (whether this specific one or something similar) will pay dividends for your recruiting game. You will notice the difference almost immediately!  
&lt;/br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;font color=&#34;grey&#34;&gt; Originally posted: January 10, 2022&lt;/font&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talent Acquisition Process Framework</title>
      <link>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/post/talent-acquisition-process-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://iopsychist.netlify.app/post/talent-acquisition-process-framework/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A good recruiter will find strong candidates. At scale, however, an organization cannot simply rely on good recruiters to fill its open positions in a reliable, time bound manner. Moreover, doing so would make it difficult to consistently plan around hiring times. With the start of 2022 seeing &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Josh_Bersin/status/1478135382298411008&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;more job postings for Recruiters than Software Engineers&lt;/a&gt;, your organization must be strategic in its approach to hiring. Furthermore, a strong TA process will increase the effectiveness of anyone on your team seeking to support recruiting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make Talent Acquisition a part of your organization&amp;rsquo;s strategic advantage, an effective Talent Acquisition &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; must be implemented. If you are facing resistance in your organization to adopting such a strategy, I lay out the business case for taking a strategic, data-driven approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business Case:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Like any human process, the recruitment process for any company is&amp;ndash;at its core&amp;ndash;uncertain. The hiring team attempts to use incomplete information on the candidate&amp;rsquo;s past experience, current knowledge, dispositional traits, and future potential. The sources of this information may have varying degrees of accuracy and reliability. The candidate may exhibit different levels of performance during the interview process for reasons outside the awareness of the hiring team &amp;ndash; whether due to stress at the current job, activity in their personal life, even for such reasons of poor sleep or a
bad commute. These inconsistencies in performance are, to a larger degree than most would like to admit, unrepresentative of on-the-job-performance. Each of the guesses, estimates, and inferences that the hiring team makes during the recruiting process open the door to uncertainty, bias, and error. Not to mention, the candidate is forming judgements based on impressions from the interviewers. Even if recruitment has gone well for a position whereby the team has accurately defined their needs, sourced quality candidates, and effectively narrowed in on the strongest candidate, the candidate may not choose to ultimately join the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of a strong recruitment process is to minimize the &lt;em&gt;noise&lt;/em&gt; associated with the selection process and to maximize the likelihood that the selected candidate chooses to join the company. In the face of such uncertainty, the process itself should not add to noise in the overall system. Rather, it should open a window to the &lt;em&gt;signals&lt;/em&gt; that will allow the astute observer to understand the activity within their practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an organization with multiple open positions and multiple team members supporting recruiting, this means &lt;strong&gt;standardization&lt;/strong&gt; of practices. The actions of one recruiter should align with the actions of another. The milestones for one job should not differ substantially from the milestones of another. Failing to do this is costly. What happens when one recruiter gets sick, takes vacation, or leaves the organization? How does their coworker jump in and know what&amp;rsquo;s going on? If there is no understanding of metrics, how does the organization know where to put its resources? If there is no sense for time to hire, how does the team know whether they are outperforming the market or not? If new hires are not succeeding in the position, how does the company know where the function is broken in order to make changes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adopting a framework that enables consistent processes allows for good data to be captured on all parts of the process, thus opening a window to answer these questions. You may be collecting such data already, but without this standardization what does time to hire mean, in aggregate, across your organization? Is it one day because you only add candidates into the system once they&amp;rsquo;ve completed all interviews and you want to make an offer? Is it 120 days because you sometimes don&amp;rsquo;t bother marking them as hired since you&amp;rsquo;d rather get started with their onboarding than make a quick clerical adjustment to the system? What if your ATS tells you that 65% of your hires come from LinkedIn Job Postings, your most expensive vendor, when really you haven&amp;rsquo;t captured source details for 50% of your top performing hires? Do you invest more in LinkedIn and hope to get top performers? Or do you go with you gut and invest in job fairs since you have a feeling that your best hires came through your college recruiting efforts? That&amp;rsquo;s a tough call, and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to be if you consistently practice good data hygiene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does this enable success? It allows your team members to collaborate, helping each other out on the those tough to fill roles. It allows new hires to quickly get up to speed with what, exactly, your process is. It allows junior members to provide a similar candidate experience as your tenured veterans. &lt;mark&gt;Essentially, a good process &amp;lsquo;bakes in&amp;rsquo; best practices&amp;ndash;reducing onboarding times and building institutional knowledge that transcends any one team member.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once a solid TA process has been established, you can begin collecting data on what works for your organization. Stayed tuned for further posts on what this looks like and how to implement it in your position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key Tenets:&lt;br&gt;
The key tenets of an effective TA Process are visibility and traceability. Remember, good data in &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; good data out&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
